<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-20T19:14:57+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kerri Plays Games</title><subtitle>Welcome to Kerrigan Fairbairns video and table top game reviews! </subtitle><author><name>Kerrigan Fairbairn</name><email>kerriganfair@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Lighting A Fire With Ember</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-07-14/Lighting-a-Fire-With-Ember" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lighting A Fire With Ember" /><published>2020-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020-07-14/Lighting-a-Fire-With-Ember</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-07-14/Lighting-a-Fire-With-Ember">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2016 a relatively small studio published a relatively small game by the name of &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/339580/Ember/&quot;&gt;Ember&lt;/a&gt;. A top-down RPG that aimed to do something different. Described as “A passion project 10 years in the making” I found myself oddly enthralled by it. Warning, potential spoilers below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game introduces it’s story immediately with a captivating opening sequence comparable to Windwaker or the first Witcher with the aim of pulling you into it’s world, for me it succeeded. The next thing you know, you’re waking up in a crypt, your crypt. That’s right, you’re undead. Ressurected by a monk who introduces himself as Coren, you begin to navigate your way through the labyrinthian tomb that holds as many mysteries as your head can contain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here’s where I take a break to discuss some of the more abstract concepts within Ember. What Ember does extremely well is it’s combat, it’s apparent immediately that the space bar is going to become a close personal friend as you keep your eyes above each character trying to anticipate what will happen next and how best to respond to it. Throughout the game you will have a party of at most three characters, if you’re like me you’ll be bringing along the twins Coren and Corra. These characters can each have three skills determined by their enchanted gear, weapons, helmets and armour. Early on in the game I must admit I felt frustrated with the system, I kept looking for my skill tree, talent points or perks as I levelled up despite having been introduced to the enchantment system within the tutorial area. However, once I discovered crafting it all began to make sense. Each available skill would appear beneath the character bar located at the top of the screen and you could pause the combat at any moment, click or drag the desired skill to the desired target, unpause and watch the fight unfold. If you’re familiar to action time-based combat from Baldur’s gate, this was that but elegant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I touched on a small handful of concepts there that will need to be further discussed, and we’ll start with the characters. Progression in Ember was simple, you gain experience, you level up, you spend attribute points. There are only four attributes in Ember and it’s likely you’ll focus on two for each of your characters. I decided the best way to utilise my party was to include a healer, a ranger and a champion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My champion was the Lighbringer, the protagonist of the story. This character relied on the strength and vitality attributes. Strength determined the level of weapon and heavy armour he could use as well as the damage dealt, and vitality determined his hitpoint total. For his build I kept him equipped with greatswords and greataxes depending on what enchantments I needed, and usually went with something that had a powerful interrupt or knockdown ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My ranger was Coren, the monk who ressurects you at the beginning of the game. Coren relied on dexterity and I kept vitality up just to keep him alive. Dexterity was the deciding factor for ranged weapons and light armour and Coren’s weapons changed between crossbows and bows as I found or crafted upgrades, though I tended to prefer crossbows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally my healer was Corra, Coren’s twin sister. Her primary attribute was intelligence and as is the trend, vitality to support her. Intelligence determined the quality of robes and magic weapons she could use and also influenced the power of healing and damaging spells. She would primarily use a staff, but her healing enchantment was almost always kept in the helmet slot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to beat the game relatively easily with this trio on normal difficulty, dying only in encounters where I was underlevelled or undergeared, or on the occasional boss encounter. As I improved my understanding of the game I was able to take on more and more difficult challenges within it. The combat system displayed skills as icons, and the enemies had access to the same skills as the player, this meant over time you could learn what a skill did from it’s icon alone and that meant you could react to them in combat. Timing interrupts or knockdowns to cancel a powerful enemy ability, or timing a heal to proc as soon as a large amount of damage had been dealt became an entertaining puzzle to solve during a fight. Collecting those skills was a different matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all good RPG games do, Ember included a crafting system, and as I am wont to, I was initially intimidated by it, that was until I collected a few recipes. Now, recipes were not required to create items in Ember, if you had the ingredients and used them at the right work station you could create the item, and once I’d found several recipes I was able to piece the others together myself. Crafting is fundamentally the best way to obtain gear that not only performs well but also has the enchantments you want for your characters. Upgrading your gear for greater damage but replacing what has become an essential skill for your playstyle can be super frustrating, and it was exactly that which kept Corra in a level 5 hood for 15 levels just to keep a strong healing skill. Crafting was a simple enough process though and ingredients were relatively common, common enough that I was able to make a new weapon for each of my characters with only a little bit of farming after I’d accomplished enough in each area to level up to where I’d need them, this was less true for armour but my priority is in killing the enemy fast enough that I’d be okay. Some shops did carry interesting weapons and armour that I ended up acquiring for a short time, and enemies could also drop a few uniques that came in useful, but ultimately I finished the game with a completely crafted set of gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At it’s core Ember appeared to me to be a love letter to classic RPG games imploring them to take their best features and streamline them. But moving away from the abstract game elements, let’s talk about story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the story, but it wasn’t revolutionary. If I could liken it to a more popular example I would liken it to Legend of Zelda Ocarina of Time. It was a typical hero quest to save the world that lead you on a collectathon for people who knew better than you what to do, but had to rely on you to get it done. This collectathon ultimately takes you all across the world to long forgotten places in order to reunite the people under your common goal. It was a good story, it’s just hard to argue it’s originality. With that being said, the theme was pleasant and interesting and the additional content surrounding the story kept me engaged well enough. Sadly, I cannot say the same for my companions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coren and Corra were sadly underdeveloped. I felt little genuine connection with them, and my options for party members seemed relatively slim. I kept them because they were the ones introduced to me first, and they were twins, for a time I had to leave one of them behind and travel with a stranger and I’ll admit it felt wrong to separate them, but not because I knew much about them. Where other RPGs of a similar style would interrupt the gameplay to drag you along on companion quests, or interject with some pivotal character development plot, Ember never did. Sure the characters had unique voice lines, and occasional dialogue options with NPCs in the world, but in the end there just wasn’t enough. I could’ve travelled with any characters I wanted and it would have felt the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the protagonist, there’s not a lot to say. There’s no character creation so you’re stuck with the gangly undead creature who climbs out of his coffin at the beginning of the game, short of a few different armour models there’s nothing to distinguish him as the hero beyond his unique race of Lightbringer. By the end of the game you’re just as confused about who he is as you are when you start and it was very underwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above characters aside, the antagonist of the Darkbringer was genuinely a breath of fresh air, this character felt like he had purpose, influence and even development, and interracting with him just makes the rest of the cast all that more disappointing. I owe my completion of the game largely to trying to understand the motivations and actions of the Darkbringer, as well as the world in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, whilst the characters were underdeveloped the world itself was not. The atmosphere was beautiful, and despite the dated appearance of the graphics the themes were incredible, the City of Light blew me away when I first stepped into it and I was never left disappointed as I found new areas to explore. Just as much of the world however was contained in the books and scrolls littering the place. I read everything I came across. There were encylcopedia on the races of the world, detailed accounts of wars fought and philosophical debates on the outcomes of them. Whoever wrote for the game was a genius and my connection to the world as the Lightbringer was far more established in the literature of the past than it was of the actions of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of my first play through I’d only put in 25 hours, it was a shorter game than I’m used too but it was very self-contained and other than the disappointment of the characters, rather enjoyable. I’d recommend playing the game at least once just to experience the world within it. There are a number of secrets too and some incredibly entertaining side quests such as hunting the dragon hunter, or helping true love succeed following a wonderful goose chase. If you enjoy modern RPG games and have never given cRPGs a go, or you enjoy cRPGs and want to experience something a little less intense, Ember is a surefire add to your collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you made it this far, thank you for reading, and may the light be with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/GGpTNOa.png?1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kerrigan Fairbairn</name><email>kerriganfair@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Back in 2016 a relatively small studio published a relatively small game by the name of Ember. A top-down RPG that aimed to do something different. Described as “A passion project 10 years in the making” I found myself oddly enthralled by it. Warning, potential spoilers below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flashback To Pandora, A Borderlands Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019-04-05/Flashback-to-Pandora,-a-Borderlands-Review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flashback To Pandora, A Borderlands Review" /><published>2019-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019-04-05/Flashback-to-Pandora,-a-Borderlands-Review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019-04-05/Flashback-to-Pandora,-a-Borderlands-Review">&lt;p&gt;As you may or may not know, and if you spend any time on the internet at all I’m erring towards may, a new borderlands game was recently announced. For some people this is great news, for other people it’s mildly interesting. I fall into the latter category. That being said, several of my friends stand by borderlands as one of their favourite titles and though I last played it several years ago shortly after it came out I thought I’d give it another go. What follows are my thoughts regarding Borderlands, how it played, what I enjoyed, and what I feel it could have done better. I hope to follow this post up with a sequel after playing Borderlands 2 and eventually we’ll see what happens with Borderlands 3 as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So without further ado, let’s start. There will be spoilers, the game is a decade old, you’ll be okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Character select is seamlessly done with a pleasant bus ride across Pandora, you’re on your way to a small town called Fyrestone where you’ll start your search for the Vault. All you know about the vault is… well not a lot. You know it’s basically a myth and promises grand treasures, if it’s even real. But this is a videogame and you’re set up as a vault hunter, so it’s not too difficult to appreciate the premonition of the vault being real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, you select your character and the game introduces you to a couple of core concepts, the first being the ECHO system (This thing powers your HUD and communications and was a nice way to apply a logical in-game explanation for why you have a floating bar of health on your screen at all times) and the next being the New-U stations, a form of insurance that can rebuild you in case of death, at a %-cost against your current monetary value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was by all means a pretty nice introduction, CL4P-TP (The iconic robot friend) then throws you straight into action, takes you to a crate where you’ll pick up your first weapon and leads you to Fyrestone, which is currently under seige by bandits. There’s no tutorial on how to shoot, dodge or use your ability yet (as you don’t have it) but the panic of being thrown into a gun-fight is plenty enough education. You do what you know best, you point and click. When it boils down to it, that’s what Borderlands is, a straight up shoot-em-up with some story attached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I’ll let you know that I chose Lilith as my character, I didn’t give much thought to the choice gameplay wise, she was the only female and that’s just my preference, needless to say it didn’t appear that the choice of character had any effect on the story and as such I haven’t felt the need to go back and try the others. As you start progressing the story and doing side-missions from bounty boards the game will introduce you to new things through tool-tips on the screen. These were things like Scooter’s Catch-A-Ride or your characters core ability at level 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lilith’s ability is called “Phasewalk”, it allows Lilith to move quickly from one place to another invisibly, but she can’t jump whilst doing it. This ability can be augmented with artifacts to cause an elemental area of effect attack on entering and exiting the phasewalk. Overall, I mostly just used this to speed myself up getting around places and felt it didn’t offer much of an impact to be used aggressively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forwarding a bit we’ve progressed more of the story and been introduced to some more of the characters. Marcus, who drove us to Fyrestone and leads the gun market on pandora, Dr Zed (Who apparently is not in any way Dr Ned) who sells medical supplies and shields, TK Baha a blind but lovable redneck, Scooter owner of Catch-A-Ride, Taniss and some others (who unfortunately were not impactful enough for me to remember). The story I felt was mediocre. I wasn’t invested in any of the characters stories (excluding Taniss who I’ll go on about soon) and the only thing it had going for it was the search for the vault. We find what we’re told is a part of a Key to the vault by a Cortana-like hologram in your ECHO and are encouraged to seek out help to find the other pieces. This hunt takes you to Taniss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now at this point if you’ve been doing side-missions you’ll already have been introduced to Taniss via a mission to hunt down the Echo recording she left around the Arid Badlands. These recordings were genuinely one of my favourite additions to the game and are what helped me invest any sort of relationship between myself and Taniss when we eventually met. Taniss is an eccentric by nature, and crazy by consequence. She’s a scientist who we are led to believe works for the Dahl Corporation (a name you’ll see littered on trash-bins, yes that’s a pun, and also on some weapons) and who was tasked with finding the vault in order to obtain technology that is thought would help Dahl to compete with or even beat Atlas, their biggest competitor. This mission has led to Taniss being abandoned with less-than-civilised folk to help her with her search. So when Taniss eventually double crosses you it actually comes as a surprise but it’s reassuring to know that when her plan falls through and she is kept as a captive she still considers you a friend and helps you to put things right. Despite being verifiably insane, Taniss is a genuine character, fiercely independent and wonderfully charming to talk too, and it’s a damned shame that the same attention to character wasn’t applied to the rest of the cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story resolves with a dissapointing bossfight, Commander Steele of the mercanary army you’ve begun fighting since your first steps into Old Haven reaches the vault first and opens it, letting out a creature known as the Destroyer. The Destroyer immediately kills Steele robbing you of a satisfying revenge plot and then turns it’s attention to you. The ECHO ghost convinces you that you can beat it whilst it’s weakened in this world, and what follows is one of the most boring boss fights I’ve ever encountered. Steps were made to make the fight more interesting than the rest of the gunfights, such as giant tentacles that can be broken by shooting their weak points, but beyond that it was a single stage of repetitive combat that took too long as I’d ran out of Sniper Ammo on my way there and couldn’t seem to produce more during the fight. I ended up finishing the fight by shooting it repeatedly for several minutes with a gun called The Dove (a repeater pistol that doens’t consume ammo) that I’d kept in case of this exact emergency. The Destroyer dies, there was no great treasure and you sell your key to Tannis so she can look after it for the next presumably 200 years…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, this review probably colours the game in a dim shade of grey. That would be a fair assessment too if all you cared about was the game delivering you a good story. But let’s talk about the biggest selling point of Borderlands… The Guns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion Borderlands felt like an experiment in exciting gun-play from a company that were still trying to find their feet in the game development scene, and so they tacked on a half-decent story with a half-decent cast (kudos to their diversity though, and gentle touches on issues such as sexism). As for the experiment… the gun play was actually really fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience was fairly limited to switching between snipers and revolvers, because that’s generally my comfort zone with shooters. I want to do as much damage as possible in a single hit so I don’t have to worry about any consequences, Lilith was great for this. If things got too hot I could phasewalk away and take some more pot-shots. I’d encountered many guns but ended up sticking with a level 23 sniper rifle for the majority of the game as it had stats that just couldn’t be beaten. That being said I played around with all of the options and found that running down a mob of skags with a combat rifle, taking out a swarm of rakk with a shotgun or blowing up psychos with a rocket launcher were all fun situations to be in. However, nothing quite beat the thrill of finding a boss and sniping him dead in 3 or 4 headshots. This is what I felt the game was all about and this is where the game delivered the most entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the initial game, you might have  guess that I’d picked up the Zombie Island DLC featuring Dr Ned… This story was actually better than the core-game story though it featured a much smaller arc, less characters and fewer locations. The story was well contained, the plot twist was fun to experience and the hat-tips to established cultural icons like scooby-doo were well received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally before I summarise I’ll briefly touch on the graphics, because I feel if you’ve read this far and have realised I haven’t brought them up yet there’s probably something wrong with me… and that would be fair. Borderlands has an iconic style that’s hard to miss, it’s a rough-shod hand-drawn cell-shaded style that has won over many fans of the game in it’s history and I have to say I loved it too. It was charming and it helped to establish the games cartoony atmosphere and despite this it wasn’t too much that it would detract from the darker subtones the game intended to display alongside that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to summarise. Borderlands could have been an excellent game, it was charming, it nailed it’s core element and it was a breath of fresh air from the more grim shooting games it could be said to compete with. However, it fell down on story and character development and from a game that’s core element is no more than a fun gameplay feature this was dissapointing. The DLC did improve on the writing and characters and the core game did feature a diverse cast which were benefits, but I felt the world was too abstract and the player investment just wasn’t there. The resolution to the story was extremely poor to boot. I’m looking forward to playing the sequel though as I’m hopeful that Gearbox were able to learn from this first experience and improve on all the areas I’ve discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and if you have any thoughts yourself please share them with me via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:me@kerrigan.im&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;. I’d love to hear them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m off to Catch-A-Ride.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kerrigan Fairbairn</name><email>kerriganfair@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">As you may or may not know, and if you spend any time on the internet at all I’m erring towards may, a new borderlands game was recently announced. For some people this is great news, for other people it’s mildly interesting. I fall into the latter category. That being said, several of my friends stand by borderlands as one of their favourite titles and though I last played it several years ago shortly after it came out I thought I’d give it another go. What follows are my thoughts regarding Borderlands, how it played, what I enjoyed, and what I feel it could have done better. I hope to follow this post up with a sequel after playing Borderlands 2 and eventually we’ll see what happens with Borderlands 3 as well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Enderal First Impressions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019-03-30/Enderal-First-Impressions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enderal First Impressions" /><published>2019-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019-03-30/Enderal-First-Impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019-03-30/Enderal-First-Impressions">&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk to you about a recent development in story telling and adventure from the breathtaking world of Enderal a small continent in the land of Vyn where the gods are dead and the wheel of time is due to complete one more full rotation. In order to do this, there will doubtless be some spoilers but I’ll try my best to keep them as few as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First things first, however, let me express to you my wonder in the knowledge that Enderal exists as a standalone game built on top of a staple of the modern RPG… That’s right, Skyrim. As a standalone game built using the creation kit and resources from the modding community as well as the team put together by SureAI, if you own Skyrim you can play Enderal for free! It is hard to overstate how impressive the work done by this collaboration of artists, writers and engineers is in the first place, but infinitely more with this knowledge applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now though, we shall begin our tale. It starts in a field, by a wagon, at the bottom of a path and it starts as all life starts, as a child. Walking up the path you will meet your first curiosity in what we’ll call a caricature of the player’s family and I’ll leave it at that. Suddenly torn away from the scene by the hard tug of a loading screen you wake to find yourself on a boat (Morrowwind fans, where are you at?), stowing away behind the storage crates feeding off of what little you can get away with without being caught, a criminal refugee. This is where you’ll be presented with the character creation and sadly for those of you who are fans of the Khajiit, Orks, Argonians and Elves you’ll be dissapointed to find humans are the only species. There are however a small number of races to choose from each with their own benefits and a brief history of their origins which helps set the mood for the adventure you’re about to be forced into. For my first playthrough, I went with Qyranian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to skim over the rest of the story elements that lead you to this point, some things happen and you find yourself on the continent of Enderal, the last bastion of the Holy Order and the one country left that doesn’t seem to be at war with itself. The game at this point walks you through another dream and sets you upon a ruined temple where you’ll be introduced to some of the games core features through a narrative tutorial experience; including an introduction to the levelling system, and magic which are both needed. Which leads me to the next part of this review the breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Enderal: Forgotten Stories and much unlike Skyrim, there are negative impacts of being a creature capable of magic and this comes in the form of Arcane Fever. From a gameplay standpoint this fever is the difference between being an immortal god and a truer representation of a flawed mortal being. Magical humans are inflicted with sensitivity to healing magics, and not just from spells but potions too. Healing yourself with potions and healing spells or standing around areas of highly concentrated magic will cause your fever to increase and the only way to diminish the impacts are to stave it off with a solution of Ambrosia; an expensive substance produced by Arcanists and not something you’re likely to find copious amounts of in the wild. So healing yourself with magic isn’t always ideal or the best course of action, how about pausing the fight to eat 100 cheese wheels instead? Well I’m afraid that’s not going to help you much either and your mortality shall remain very much that. In Enderal, you only regenerate health outside of combat by sleeping, or by being Sated. A cheesewheel might sate you for a short time, but you’ll need to eat again at some point in order to maintain that. Raw foods can be used to heal small portions of health rapidly after combat but the effects of cooked food are longer lasting and more ideal to longer adventures outside of civilised areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, chasing the dream of becomming an Immortal Light-Born has suddenly become much more difficult, but nonetheless you’ve left the ruined temple, a few more things happen and you meet your first core character of the story, Jesper Dal’Varek. At this point the game has already started to feel vastly different to the base it was built upon, and as it was for me my connection to the story line was strong. Jesper will spin you a tale about why he’s out in the wilderness and asks you to help him with his task, a task that introduces you to the problems Enderal and the world at large are currently dealing with. Though this task reveals a small part of the puzzle, it represents a much larger image than first impressions would have you believe. After helping Jesper he introduces you to some more of the pivotal cast and you discover more about yourself than you had ever expected and though you are no Dragonborn your sense of self-importance at this point should be growing. This is something the story does exceedingly well as your role in the story leads more and more towards the outcome you as a player drive it towards. Before long you will have met several other characters who are a wonder to interact with and you will have started to explore more of the beautifully crafted world the game is set in. At this point the game really opens up to you and I’ll say no more of the story from here on in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’ll talk about some of the features I really enjoyed in Enderal. Firstly, I’d like to talk about the writing. The story is genuinely compelling which is something I felt Skyrim lacked (It’s hard not to compare the game to Skyrim considering it’s the base it was built upon) and felt more along the lines of a more classic RPG such as Dragon Age: Origins or Divinity. However, the urgency of the storyline quest was put on hold when story characters had to accomplish tasks by themselves where the player wasn’t necessary or did not have the means to help. This was a brilliant addition in my opinion, waiting a couple of days in-game for a magister to decode some old instructions or for a companion to take some time to recover from a difficult situation gave you the player an excuse to spend your time elsewhere. For me, that time was mostly spent hunting down wanted criminals and exploring more old ruins and ultimately it was this series of gaps that really funnelled in the meagre wealther I accumulated in order to build my characters strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which takes me on to the second feature. In Skyrim, you might be familiar with the idea that your skills increase as you use them. Pick some locks, and your lockpicking skill increases, hit things with a sword and you develop a better understanding of One-Handed… This isn’t the same in Enderal and though it might seem counter-intuitive I felt it added a level of interaction to the game that helped improve the over-all atmosphere and investment. So let’s go into character development. First things first I’ll discuss levelling up and talents. Levelling up in Enderal is pretty simple. You engage in content that rewards you with Experience Points such as completing a quest, discovering a new location or just straight up killing something. Get enough experience points and you level up, it’s the classic grind. When you level up you are rewarded with some points. Crafting Points, Learning Points and Memory Points. Crafting points can be used to increase skills such as Enchantment or Handicraft (Smithing). Learning Points go onto skills such as Light-Armor, One-Handed or Magic. And finally, Memory points are spent on talents. Now this is still a first impressions so I won’t go into detail about the various talents, schools of magic or the likes as I have yet to experience so much of that as my first playthrough was completed as the good old Sword and Board champion. Now spending these points isn’t as straight-forward as opening up an interface and deciding where to put them, instead you have to acquire “Learning books” from merchants, out in the wild or as quest rewards. Using a learning book consumes a point and the books are split between Apprentice (up to level 25), Adept (up to level 50), Expert (up to level 75) and Master (up to 100). The books get increasingly more expensive through each tier and as such act as a wonderful counter-balance to the ever increasing wealth problem that Skyrim presented the player with. So my time spent at a pause in the storyline was spent gathering books with which to improve my character’s ability to fight and craft. By the end of the story I had managed to reach 86 Handicraft, 76 Light-Armor and 69 One-Handed. I still had several points left over as I hadn’t acquired enough books or money to buy them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To expand on that though, there was another feature that Enderal offers and that’s armours with Set-Bonuses. Now those of you who are fans of some more classic RPGs such as Neverwinter Nights, Dungeon Siege and Diablo might be familiar with this idea. You gather multiple pieces of armour from the same set, and you get additional bonuses. It’s a pretty simple but very effecitve addition and even though I had the ability to craft armour that was more powerful than any individual set piece, I still kept several set pieces around for their additional bonsuses. One such set was the Skaragg set, a set of heavy armour for which I had no other purpose than to boost my handicraft skill, allowing me to raise the 86 I had gathered through books to 100! Another set I used for fighting raised my light-armour skill by a total of 17%, which raised my armour rating to that of a level comparable to that of a base heavy armour alternative when combined with my talents!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are Talents anyway? They’ve come up a couple of times in this ramble already so I’ll use this time to explain them. Talents are what Enderal provides you with in place of Perks. Every time you level up you get one memory point. Meditating will allow you to spend that point on an affine tree of your choice. Affine trees are specialised into certain areas, for example, I spent most of my points in the Blade Dancer and Vagrant trees. These trees gave me the most benefits to One-Handed and Light Armour and were best suited to my play style. Combining certain affine trees will reward you with an extra effect too! Among the standard passive affects you might be used to however, these trees can grant you talents, and talents are the alternative provided in place of Skyrim’s Thu’um. These are active abilities that you can select from your magic menu and use during combat. The cooldowns on these are independent of each other, allowing you to combine them in creative ways. One such example provided by the game is combining Snaketongue Oil, a talent that lets you throw a small bottle of slippery oil onto the ground that causes enemies who walk through it to fall over before applying a small duration slow debuff to them, with fire! So now your enemies are on the floor and burning, what fun. There are a good number of talents to take and explore with and I felt that system (though clunky) was a great way to add more strategy to the combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which allows me to segue into this next part, the combat. Combat encounters in Enderal are (or at least for me) quite frankly much more difficult than what you may be used too if your experience with RPGs is limited to games like Skyrim. Instead, it’s far closer to the experience of a CRPG like Baldur’s Gate where you have to actively think about how you’re going to succeed. This is accomplished in the game not just by it’s higher base difficulty than Skyrim, but also through the afforementioned features. You can’t just pause the game and chug several health potions because you’ll increase your arance fever to the point of death and you can’t eat a dozen cheese wheels because they’ll do nothing until combat has ended. Likewise the enemies are tougher, some of them do incredible amounts of damage so timing your shield blocks, bashes and dodges is far more important (even in heavy armour tanking some enemies is no more than an exercise of futility) and knowing when to strike can change the outcome rapidly. This was further compounded by the fact that progressing your character couldn’t be readily done in a dungeon. If you levelled up you could spend a memory point sure, and that point might make the difference between being one-shot by a tough enemy and staying a live for the second hit… but to really improve you have to acquire a copious amount of books and that was best done in the city of Ark and not in the depths of some flooded cavern somewhere. So you had to leave to gather things to sell in order to return and improve before you could go out again, this definitely stopped me wandering off between dungeons as the enemies level with you, but your skills don’t. Over-all I thought the balance of this was well established and made the encounters all the more rewarding for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly I’ll talk about the environments. You start out in the sun coast, a quiet little area almost forgotten about by the forces that be, but it sets your expectations of beauty going in. There’s a lot more green, than you might be used to, and a lot of colour too. Exploring more of the world you can find a variety of biomes including deserts and tundras. Flowers add a lot of colour and there are plenty of them, as well as a fitting variety of wildlife that really improves the atmosphere provided by the fauna overall. The design of key locations like Ark or Duneville felt organic and provided a good impression of the people who lived in them and travelling around them became comfortably familiar. The wilds were full of life, and there was never a time when I had to walk somewhere that I was bored or disinterested as there was always something to chase, fight or just admire. And whilst walking was essential at times (Because Enderal disables fast travel by default) the game provides many ways to get around. You could teleport via scroll to many areas or fly on the back of a Myrad a graceful creature trained to transport people much like the Gryphons in World of Warcraft or the Silt Striders from Morrowwind. This allievated the concerns about travel greatly and it meant that I rarely had to walk so far as to actually get bored walking; and if you do get bored walking you could also buy a horse to get around quicker, though I never did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to my summary. Enderal was in it’s first play through (Because I most certainly will be jumping right back into it) a refreshing experience from a modern RPG game and if I had to draw up a comparison I would say it would sit comfortably somewhere between Skyrim and Divinity: Original Sin. The game hearkens back to several ideas from Classic RPGs whilst presenting you with the simpler more intuitive control schemes from a Modern RPG. The story was gripping and exciting and features a very interesting narrative on the state of humanity as a whole, however, it suffered from some common fantasy cliches. This shouldn’t be taken as a criticism though as it still offers a thrilling experience all the same. The main story line characters and companions were well written, and for the most part you could discover a lot about them and their motivations which I enjoyed greatly. The environments were a pleasure to be in, comfortably familiar and well presented. And finally, the character progression did feel like an obstacle, but it felt like a necessary hurdle to maintain balance and improved the sense of reward and gratification felt when the impacts of your progression were demonstrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I would definitely recommend giving Enderal at least one playthrough. It was a wonderful experience that if you own Skyrim already (and let’s face it, who doesn’t?) it’ll cost you nothing but time. My first playthough I reached level 35, kept mostly to the story line and still spent 70 hours of my time within it. Which in retrospect is a pleasant surprise and clearly demonstrates that Enderal is much more than just a “Mod”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in playing Enderal yourself you can find out more about it at &lt;a href=&quot;https://sureai.net&quot;&gt;SureAI.net&lt;/a&gt; or you can download the game now on &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/933480/&quot;&gt;steam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this far, thank you very much for sticking through it. I’d love to hear your thoughts on Enderal too, if you have anything to say send me an &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:me@kerrigan.im&quot;&gt;e-mail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again, and walk blessed.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/Y12npgj.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kerrigan Fairbairn</name><email>kerriganfair@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Today I want to talk to you about a recent development in story telling and adventure from the breathtaking world of Enderal a small continent in the land of Vyn where the gods are dead and the wheel of time is due to complete one more full rotation. In order to do this, there will doubtless be some spoilers but I’ll try my best to keep them as few as possible.</summary></entry></feed>